<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEXT SYSTEM "https://cocoon.huma-num.fr/schemas/Archive.dtd">
<TEXT id="cocoon-268011f0-1a4f-4d51-b282-a99653b507f7" xml:lang="nru">
<HEADER></HEADER>
    <FORM kindOf="ortho">Eyishei jjo, Lhiddi ddimi jjo Lhiddi bi niq mae, aeggi? Lhiddi tee jjo xilee du megu mae, eyishei. Tiq, xilee medu, khazzei du, nulee du, zzeilee poq, muzzei poq, mussi poq tee la poq guq mae. Tiq, hin tee mejjo. Yi luq guhin jjaq mejjo. Xidu jjo yi boq beq bbi ssogu mae. Tiage gguq guhin mejjo. Naq tee eyishei jjaq xi medu niq mae. Tiq, khazzei du, zzeilee poq, muzzei poq, nulee du, nuhun du tee la  yi gua ji la. 
        Ggiggi jjo, tiq, hin tee teegho ddeevu lecee, tugho ddeevu lecee. Tiq, yi guq ddeevu Lhiddi ddimi cee bi, tiq, teevu nee leyi teeji gua ji la - yii! - teevu teeyi jjo, osigu xidu ssoho ddi! Teexxi gi ddeeli bbi bi, uaq ddeeda hee. Tiq, tee gi leli, tiq, yi guhin teevu nee tiage jji teekee, tiage leggu, tiage lede teeji. Tiq, hin tiage gguhin jjo ddeevu teegho hinq, ddeevu tugho hinq, zhei tee tee niq ggeghuae teeji jjo, tiq, tiage tee tee niq teeshae guq niq mae. Xilee lupu jjo tee niq piq niq mae. Tiq, teegho nee xidu soq. Tiq, xichuae muq.
        Wodda jjo, xichuae jjo muq guq paeddi jjo, hin medu niq mae. Tiq, ggiggi nee Lhiddi Ddimi jjo xichuae jjaq jjaq. Xichuae jjo. On tee niq, tiq, nulee jjo, xichuae jjo, muzzei jjo, zzeilee jjo, mussi jjo, aezo meni wuguzalia jjo niq ssei mae. Hachi nguabbae!  Nguabbae kheubbae jjo niq ssei. Eyishei, Lhiddi ddimi gho teegho jjo. Tiq, ssono haeshi jjo, aezo meni jjo mae. Ha tee, yeyo jjo, mejjo ddeeso mejjo. Du wu bi jjo niq ssei, du mewu bi mejjo niq ssei. Lhiddi ddimi gho jjo tee niq jjo niq. Muddi jjo jjaq niq, Lhiddi ddimi jjo. 
        Eyishei, tiq noq, ssogho meni hin lecee bi, Lhiddi Ddimi gho cee. Eyishei, Lhiddi ddimi tee hin nu ruaeq guq zimu. Hin nu ruaeq gua, ggi nee tae teegho lecee, teegho lecee, tugho lecee, teegho Naq ddeexxi lecee, teegho Bbe ddeexxi lecee, tugho Hae ddeexxi lecee teezzee. Ssono, Naq tee haeshi Todee, Zzeibbo, jjabi jjo niq.
    </FORM>
    <TRANSL xml:lang="cn">以前永宁乡叫永宁，对呀？以前永宁是不会种水稻的。那么，不种水稻，种玉米，种黄豆，种小麦，种大麦，种燕麦就只会种这些。但是没有很多人。会犁地的人也不多。种水稻的时候需要用牛来耙地。也没有会做田埂的人。以前摩梭人不怎么种水稻。所以种玉米，种小麦，种大麦，种黄豆，种豆子，只会做这些。
        后来后来人就从这里来一个，那里来一个。然后，如果会做什么的人来永宁乡的话，这个人这样做了后——咦！——这个人在做，我们也试试种水稻 吧！说去这家看看吧，全部都去那家。所以去那家看了，然后会做的那个人装水在田里，弄田埂，拉好两边的田埂放着。然后，他们做田埂的人，一个站这里，一个站那里，土挖上来这样放着，然后田埂是这么长的。水田是这样平的。那么，在这里学种水稻。然后水稻成熟了。
        以前好像水稻会成熟了，只是没种。‎‎那后来后来永宁的大米就很好。有水稻。像这样有黄豆，有大米，有大麦，有小麦，有燕麦，有各种五谷杂粮。有五种谷类！大概有五六种，以前在永宁这里。然后，现在还是有，任何东西都有。有谷类，有土豆，都有。能种的话就有，不能种的话就没有。‎‎永宁乡是有这些的。永宁乡的土地是好的。
        ‎‎以前无论从哪里来的人都来永宁。‎‎据说以前我们永宁人很少。由于人很少，后来才从这里来，从这里来，从那里来，从这里来一家摩梭，从这里来一家普米，从那里来一家汉族住在这里。现在还是很多摩梭，托知、泥鳅沟。</TRANSL>
    <TRANSL xml:lang="en">In the past, Yongning township was called Yongning, right? ‎‎Yongning  did not grow rice, in the past. We didn't grow rice, we grew corn, we grew soyabeans, we grew wheat, we grew barley, we grew oats, we only grew these. But there were not many people who could plough with a bullock. When people plant rice paddies, they have to use an ox to harrow the land. There was nobody who could make the ridges between paddy fields. Na in the past did not really grow rice. We grew corn, we grew wheat, we grew barley, we grew soybeans, we grew beans, we would only grow these.
        ‎‎Then later on a person came from here, a person came from there. Then, if a person came to Yongning who could do it, after this person had done it - oh! - what this person was doing, we would also have a go at planting rice paddies! ‎‎If someone said "Let's go and have a look at that family," everyone went and had a look. So everyone went to that family to look. Then the person who could do it put water on the fields, made the ridges between the paddy fields, and then built up the ridges. Well, the people who made the ridges between paddy fields, one would stand here and one would stand there, and they'd dig up the soil and place it like this, and then the ridge would be this long! The paddy fields were flat like this eh. So we learned how to plant rice paddies here. Then the rice ripened. 
        It seems that in the past rice did grow here, but people didn't plant it. Well, later on Yongning rice was very good. There was rice. So then there were soyabeans, there was rice, there was barley, there was wheat, there were oats, there were all of the 'five cereals'! Five sorts of grains! There were five or six sorts in the past, here in Yongning. Well, now there still are, we have them all. ‎‎There are grains, there are potatoes, there's nothing we don't have. ‎‎If you can grow it we have it, if you can't grow it we don't have it.  It's like this in Yongning. The soil is good in Yongning.
        In the past, people came from all over the place to Yongning. It's said that long ago there were very few people in Yongning. Because there were not many people, it was only afterwards that people came from here and came from there, a Na family came from here, a Pumi family came from here, a Han family came from there to live here. Now there are still a lot of Na, such as in Tuozhi village and Zhibo village.
    </TRANSL>
    <S id='S1'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Eyishei jjo, Lhiddi ddimi jjo, tiq, Lhiddi bi niq mae, aeggi?</FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>以前永宁乡叫永宁，对呀？</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>In the past, Yongning township was called Yongning, right?</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S2'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Lhiddi tee jjo, tiq, xilee du megu mae, eyishei. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>永宁是不会种水稻的，以前。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>‎‎Yongning, it did not grow [lit: plant] rice eh, in the past.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S3'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Tiq, xilee medu, khazzei du, nulee du, zzeilee poq, muzzei poq, mussi poq tee la poq guq mae. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>那么，不种水稻，种玉米，种黄豆，种小麦，种大麦，种燕麦就只会种这些。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>Well, (we) didn't grow [lit: plant] rice, (we) grew [lit: planted] corn, (we) grew [lit: planted] soyabeans, (we) grew [lit: sowed] wheat, (we) grew [lit: sowed] barley, (we) grew [lit: sowed] oats, (we) only grew [lit: sowed] these.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S4'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Tiq, hin tee mejjo. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>但是没有（很多）人。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>But there weren't (many) people. </TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S5'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Yi luq guhin jjaq mejjo. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>会犁地的人也不多。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>There were not many people who could plough with a bullock.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S6'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Xidu jjo, uaq yi boq beq bbi ssogu mae. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>种水稻的时候需要用牛来耙地。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>When (people) plant rice paddies, (they) have to use an ox to harrow (the land) eh.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S7'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Tiage gguq guq mejjo, hin tee.</FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>也没有会做田埂的人。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>There was nobody who could make the ridges between paddy fields.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S8'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Naq tee eyishei jjaq xi medu niq mae.</FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>以前摩梭人不怎么种水稻。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>Na, in the past they did not really grow [lit: plant] rice eh.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S9'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Tiq, khazzei du, zzeilee poq, muzzei poq, nulee du, nuhun du tee la yi gua ji la. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>所以种玉米，种小麦，种大麦，种黄豆，种豆子，只会做这些。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>So, (we) grew [lit: planted] corn, (we) grew [lit: sowed] wheat, (we) grew [lit: sowed] barley, (we) grew [lit: planted] soybeans, (we) grew [lit: planted] beans, (we) would only grow [lit: do] these.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S10'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Ggiggi jjo, tiq, hin tee teegho ddeevu lecee, tugho ddeevu lecee. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>后来后来，人就从这里来一个，那里来一个。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>‎‎Then later on a person came from here, a person came from there.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S11'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Tiq, yi guq ddeevu Lhiddi ddimi cee bi, tiq, teevu nee leyi teeji gua ji la - yii! - teevu teeyi jjo, osigu xidu ssoho ddi! </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>然后，如果会做（什么）的人来永宁乡的话，这个人（这样）做了后——咦！——这个人在做，我们也试试种水稻 吧！</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>Then, say a person came to Yongning who could do it, then, after this person had done it - oh! - what this person was doing, let's (also) have a go at planting rice paddies!</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S12'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Teexxi gi ddeeli bbi bi, uaq ddeeda hee. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>说去这家看看吧，全部都去（那家）。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>‎‎If (someone) said "Let's go and have a look at that family," everyone went (and had a look).</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S13'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Tiq, tee gi leli, tiq, yi guhin teevu nee, tiq, tiage jji teekee, tiage leggu, tiq, tiage lede teeji.</FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>所以，去那家看了，然后，会做的那个人装水在田里，弄田埂，那么，拉好（两边的）田埂放着。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>So (everyone went) to that (family) to look, then the person who could do it put water on the fields [lit: ridges], made the ridges between the paddy fields, and then built up [lit: pulled] the ridges.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S14'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Tiq, hin tiage gguhin jjo ddeevu teegho hinq, ddeevu tugho hinq, zhei tee tee niq ggeghuae teeji, tiq, tiage tee teeshae guq niq mae. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>然后，他们做田埂的人，一个站这里，一个站那里，土挖上来这样放着，然后，田埂是这么长的。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>Well, the people who made the ridges between paddy fields, one (would) stand here (and) one (would) stand there, (and they'd) dig up the soil and place it like this, and then the ridge would be this long!</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S15'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Xilee lupu jjo tee niq piq niq mae. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>水田是这样平的。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>The paddy fields were flat like this eh.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S16'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Tiq, teegho nee xidu soq. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>那么，在这里学种水稻。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>So (we) learned (how) to plant rice paddies here.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S17'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Tiq, xichuae muq. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>然后水稻成熟了。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>Then the rice ripened.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S18'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Wodda jjo, xichuae jjo muq guq paeddi jjo, hin medu niq mae. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>以前好像水稻会成熟了，只是没种。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>‎‎It seems that in the past rice did grow [lit: ripen] (here), but (people) didn't plant (it) eh.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S19'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Tiq, ggiggi nee Lhiddi ddimi jjo xichuae jjaq jjaq. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>那后来后来永宁的大米就很好。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>Well, later on Yongning rice was very good.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S20'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Xichuae jjo. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>有水稻。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>There was rice. / (We) have rice.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S21'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">On tee niq, tiq, nulee jjo, xichuae jjo, muzzei jjo, zzeilee jjo, mussi jjo, aezo meni wuguzalia jjo niq ssei mae! </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>像这样，那么，有黄豆，有大米，有大麦，有小麦，有燕麦，有各种五谷杂粮。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>‎‎In this way, then, there were soyabeans, there was rice, there was barley, there was wheat, there were oats, there were all of the 'five cereals' eh!</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S22'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Ha tee nguabbae! </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>有五种谷类！</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>Five sorts of grains!</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S23'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Nguabbae kheubbae jjo niq ssei. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>大概有五六种。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>There were five or six sorts.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S24'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Eyishei, Lhiddi ddimi gho teegho jjo. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>以前，在永宁这里。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>In the past, here in Yongning.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S25'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Tiq, ssono haeshi jjo, aezo meni jjo mae. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>然后，现在还是有，任何（东西）都有。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>Well, now there still are, (we) have (them) all eh.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S26'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Ha tee, yeyo jjo, mejjo ddeeso mejjo. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>有谷类，有土豆，都有。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>‎‎(There are) grains, there are potatoes, there's nothing (we) don't have.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S27'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Du wu bi jjo niq ssei, du mewu bi mejjo niq ssei. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>能种的话就有，不能种的话就没有。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>‎‎If (you) can grow (it we) have (it), if (you) can't grow (it we) don't have (it).</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S28'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Lhiddi ddimi gho jjo tee niq jjo niq. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>永宁乡是有这些的。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>Yongning has it like this.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S29'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Muddi jjo jjaq niq, Lhiddi ddimi jjo. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>永宁乡的土地是好的。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>The soil is good (in) Yongning.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S30'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Eyishei, tiq noq, ssogho meni hin lecee bi, Lhiddi ddimi gho cee. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>‎‎以前，无论从哪里来的人，都来永宁。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>In the past, well then, people from all over the place , (they) came to Yongning.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S31'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Ssono.  Hin tee.</FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>现在。人。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>Now. People.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S32'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Nyasigu, eyishei, Lhiddi ddimi tee hin nu ruaeq guq zimu. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>‎‎据说，以前我们永宁人很少。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>It's said that long ago there were very few people (in) Yongning.</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S33'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Hin nu ruaeq gua, ggi nee tae teegho lecee, teegho lecee, tugho lecee, teegho Naq ddeexxi lecee, teegho Bbe ddeexxi lecee, tugho Hae ddeexxi lecee teezzee. </FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>由于人很少，后来才从这里来，从这里来，从那里来，从这里来一家摩梭，从这里来一家普米，从那里来一家汉族住（在这里）。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>Because there were not many people, it was only afterwards that (people) came from here (and) came from there, a Na family came from here, a Pumi family came from here, a Han family came from there to live (here).</TRANSL>
</S>

<S id='S34'>
<FORM kindOf="ortho">Ssono, Naq tee haeshi Todee, Zzeibbo jjabi jjo niq.</FORM>
<TRANSL xml:lang='cn'>现在还是很多摩梭，托知、泥鳅沟。</TRANSL>
<TRANSL xml:lang='en'>Now there are still a lot of Na, (such as in) Tuozhi (and) Zhibo.</TRANSL>
</S>

</TEXT>